Guide to the The Danby Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Danby papers
1661-1748
1661-1684
OSB MSS 6
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.5
(3 boxes)
The papers document aspects of Danby's political career, particularly his investigation of the Popish Plot and his impeachment in 1678. They include correspondence with Robert Spencer, Earl of Sunderland on the negotiation for the Treaty of Nijmegen; letters from several members of the House of Lords on affairs of state; extracts from the correspondence of Edward Coleman and from informants' testimonies; letters and documents relating to Danby's impeachment and imprisonment, including copies of his petitions for release; and papers concerning his various offices, including muster rolls for the West Riding Militia and Treasury accounts.
Leeds, Thomas Osborne, Duke of, 1631-1712
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The majority of the papers which comprise this collection were part of a collection purchased by John Webster in 1872, and later acquired by George Moffatt. James Osborn subsequently acquired the papers, lot 355 of the Sotheby's Moffatt sale, in October 1959. The Danby Papers were given to the Beinecke Library by Mr. Osborn in 1976.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
THOMAS OSBORNE, EARL OF DANBY (1631/32-1712)
Thomas Osborne, Earl of Danby, Marquis of Carmarthen, and Duke of Leeds was born on February 20, 1631/32, the son of Sir Edward Osborne and his wife, Anne. He spent his early years at the family estate of Kiveton in Yorkshire and succeeded his father as second baronet in 1647. In 1661 he was appointed High Sheriff of Yorkshire, probably through the influence of the Duke of Buckingham, his patron. He served as a member of Parliament for York (1665-73), Joint Commissioner of Public Accounts (1667); Joint Treasurer of the Navy (1668-71), and Treasurer of the Navy (1671-73). His administrative skills earned him the favor of Charles II and in 1673 he was appointed to the office of Lord High Treasurer. A year later, he was created Earl of Danby.
As chief minister to Charles II, Danby became one of the most powerful men in English politics during the 1670s. Proud and ambitious, the Earl had few friends. Instead, he concentrated his efforts on organizing a Court party which served the Cavalier and Church interests. He was active in foreign affairs and attempted to secure the permanent adoption of a Protestant and anti-French policy. However, he failed to gain the support of Charles II, who directed the Lord Treasurer to accept subsidies from France as the price for English neutrality in the wars fought by Louis XIV.
In 1678, Danby pressed for an investigation into an alleged conspiracy against the king, the government and the Protestant religion, an episode which became known as the Popish Plot. He was responsible for securing a warrant to obtain copies of the papers of Edward Coleman, a suspected intriguer, an action which had consequences for his own political security.
The Popish Plot gave Danby's enemies a chance to strike. In December 1678, the Privy Council ordered the seizure of political and diplomatic papers belonging to Ralph Montagu, the former ambassador in Paris. The papers contained highly damaging letters written by the Lord Treasurer which revealed the French subsidy to an outraged House of Commons. Danby was accused of high treason and charged with endeavoring to introduce arbitrary government. He was described as "popishly affected" and was said to have concealed the Plot. Danby was committed to the Tower of London and refused bail by the House of Commons. He resigned from his office as Lord Treasurer in March 1679.
Danby remained in the Tower for five years, during which time he made unremitting efforts to secure his freedom, appealing to both the king and Parliament. He finally was released on bail in 1684. The order of impeachment against him was annulled a year later.
In subsequent years, Danby took an active part in opposition to the government. He was one of the seven noblemen to sign an invitation to Prince William of Orange in 1688. After the Revolution, he served as the Lord President of the Council (1688-99). He was disliked by many of his fellow courtiers, one of whom described the earl as "a thin, ill-natured ghost that haunts the king" (DNB, p. 1195).
In 1689 he was created Marquis of Carmarthen and in 1694 he became Duke of Leeds. He served as the Lord Lieutenant of the West Riding (1674-79, 1689-99), the East Riding (1691-99), and of the North Riding (1692-99). He married, in 1653, Bridget, 2nd daughter of Montagu Bertie, 2nd Earl of Lindsey, and had five daughters and three sons, among them Edward, Viscount Latimer (1655-89), and Peregrine, 2nd Duke of Leeds (1659-1734). He died on July 26, 1712 at the age of 81 and was buried at Harthill, in Yorkshire.
Scope and Contents
The Danby Papers consist of two boxes of correspondence and related papers that document aspects of the Earl of Danby's political career, in particular, his investigation of the alleged Popish Plot and his impeachment by the House of Commons in 1678. The collection also includes papers and correspondence of Danby's sons and other family members of the Godolphin line. Hence, the papers span the years 1661-1748 but the bulk of the material concerns Danby's political career in the years 1670-1684.
Series I, Danby Correspondence, 1673-1685, contains letters to and from Danby, as well as third-party correspondence of contemporary political figures. Of particular interest are three petitions Danby wrote while imprisoned in the Tower in 1681, begging the king for his release on bail and a speedy trial. As the correspondence demonstrates, Danby's political associates and friends also pressed for his release. Henry Cavendish (1631-1712), Duke of Newcastle, in a letter to Danby, promised his "reddyness to be your [i.e Danby's] Baile, and this day I was reddy in ye House to be soe." Many of the letters concern administrative and diplomatic matters, but there is some political gossip and intrigue as well. Roger Boyle (1621-1679), Earl of Orrery, wrote such a letter to Danby with the names in cipher. Fortunately, Danby decoded the cipher and wrote a key, which is with the letter. Another letter of interest, also partially in cipher, was sent to Danby by Arthur Capel (1631-1683), Earl of Essex.
Series II, Danby Papers, c. 1660-1710, consists of memoranda, drafts, and other documents from various aspects of Danby's political career. Of particular note are the papers relating to the Popish Plot, including extracts of letters of Edward Coleman, and papers concerning Danby's subsequent impeachment. Also of interest is the list of supporters and opponents in the House of Lords drawn up by Danby while he was in the Tower. He divided the Lords temporal into three columns: those Lords "for my Baile; " those "against;" and those "neuter." Not willing to leave the possible question of bail to chance, Danby also sent a memorandum of private instructions with the list and advised the bearer to "show this List of the Lords to any of the Lords abovenamed, but to no others, & I would have you keep this list to yourselfe." Together, the list and instructions provide an indication of Danby's supporters and enemies as he perceived them during his imprisonment. The series includes documents from Danby's tenure as Secretary of the Navy, mainly memoranda of expenditures; papers from Treasury, particularly for the expenses of the royal household in 1673 1675, copies of the civil list for 1696 and 1708; and an estimate for the remodeling of St. Paul's Cathedral, 1708. The series also includes memoranda and correspondence relating to the activities of the West Riding Militia, primarily 1670-80; miscellaneous documents related to affairs of state, 1670 -1700; and other papers including a piece of Tory propaganda entitled "Narrative of the growth of Whigg" from the 1690s.
Series III, Later Osborne and Godolphin Papers, 1684-1748, contains correspondence and papers concerning family matters as well as affairs of state. These include letters to Danby's son, Viscount Latimer (1674-89) and to Thomas 4th Duke of Leeds (1713-89); correspondence and wills of Sir William Godolphin (1634?-1696) and his sister Penelope; and letters to Sidney Godolphin, 1st Earl Godolphin (1645-1712).
Treaties of Nijmegen (1678-1679); Popish Plot, 1678; Great Britain -- Court and courtiers; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- 1660-1688; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- France; Great Britain -- History -- Charles II, 1660-1685; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1660-1688; Buckingham, George Villiers, Duke of, 1628-1687; Coleman, Edward, -1678; Essex, Arthur Capel, Earl of, 1631-1683; Fairfax, Henry; Fitzharris, Edward, 1648?-1681; Godolphin, William, Sir, 1634?-1696; Leeds, Thomas Osborne, Duke of, 1631-1712; Lloyd, William, 1627-1717; Loudon, Hugh Campbell, Earl of, d. 1731; Nottingham, Daniel Finch, Earl of, 1647-1730; Boyle, Roger, Earl of Orrery, 1621-1679; Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718; Sunderland, Robert Spencer, Earl of, 1640-1702; England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685: Charles II); Great Britain. Parliament. House of Lords
- Correspondence, 1673-85; Series I; 0.25; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is organized into three subseries: (1) incoming correspondence; (2) outgoing correspondence; (3) third party correspondence.
  - INCOMING CORRESPONDENCE
    - Bisset, Lady Bridget Fitzcharles, Countess of Plymouth, d. 1718. ALS to the Earl of Danby, 1680/1 Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Regarding a letter that she has been advised to send to the king.
    - Boyle, Roger, 1st Earl of Orrery, 1621- 1679. 2 ALS to the Earl of Danby, Bath, 1674 Jul 23, Jul 24 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Written in cipher with 1p. key.
    - Butler, James, 1st Duke of Ormonde, 1610- 1688. ALS to the Earl of Danby, Dublin, 1678 Jan 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Capel, Arthur, 1st Earl of Essex,1631- 1683. ALS to [Thomas Osborne, Viscount Latimer of Danby], Dublin Castle, 1673 Dec 30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Part of the letter, written in cipher, was decoded by Danby.
    - Cavendish, Henry, 2nd Duke of Newcastle, 1631-1712. ALS to the Earl of Danby, Oxford, 1680 Mar 24 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Offers himself as bail for Danby.
    - Fairfax, Henry, Deputy Lieutenant of the West Riding, Yorkshire. 3 ALS and 1 enclosure to Thomas, Earl of Danby, Wakefield and Leeds, 1678 Oct 10 -Nov 7 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Also contains "An Account of all the Arms taken from Papists and reputed Papists within the City of York and County of the same..."
    - Fitzcharles, Charles, 1st Earl of Plymouth, 1657?-80. ALS to the Earl of Danby, Saumur, 1677 Jan 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Lloyd, Sir Philip. ALS to the Earl of Danby, Covent Garden, 1679 Mar 18 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lloyd, William, Bishop of Landaff, 1637 -1710. 2 ALS to the Earl of Danby, Malham, 1678 Nov 15, Nov 18 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Concerning evidence in the murder of Sir Edmund Berry Godfrey.
    - Moore, William. 2 ALS to the Duke of Leeds, Rycott, 1687 Sep 10, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes a one page account of King James II at Magdalen College, 1687 Sep 4.
    - Shaw, John. ALS to [the Earl of Danby], 1673 Sep 26 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Spencer, Robert, 1st Earl of Sunderland, 1640-1702. 2 ALS to the Earl of Danby, Paris, [1678] Aug 4, Aug 2/12 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Negotiations prior to the Treaty of Nijmegen. The first of these letters is printed in Browning, ed. Thomas Osborne, Earl of Danby and Duke of Leeds, vol. II, Letters, (Glasgow, 1944), pp. 520-21.
    - Spencer, Robert, 1st Earl of Sunderland, 1640-1712. ALS to the Duke of Leeds, Whitehall, 1685 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Vane, W. ALS to [the Earl of Danby], Duffel, 1674 Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - OUTGOING CORRESPONDENCE
    - Osborne, Thomas, 1631-1712
      Thomas Osborne, 1st Earl of Danby, Marquis of Carmarthen, 1st Duke of Leeds
      - 6 letters (copies) to Robert Spencer, 2nd Earl of Sunderland, London, 1678 Jul 28 - Sep 11 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Concerning negotiations prior to the Treaty of Nijmegen.
      - 2 letters (copies) to Henry Fairfax and the deputy lieutenants of the West Riding, Cockpit, 1678 Nov 14, Nov 16 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - 3 petitions (copies) to Charles II, King of England and Ireland, 1681 Apr 1 to June 2 (Box 1, Folder 17)
        Pleading for his release from the Tower and for a speedy trial.
      - Letter (copy) to Charles II, King of Great Britain and Ireland, 1681 Jun 27 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Requests that Edward Fitzharris be given a reprieve of 10 to 14 days, as he and his wife were "useful witnesses against my Ld Howard, & can tell as much as any who those are who have been the chief suborners of Witnesses in all these Villanies..."
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Copley, Sir Godfrey, d. 1709 Deputy Lieutenant of the West Riding, Yorkshire. ALS to unknown recipient, [c.1672] (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Also signed by Sir John Reresby. Regarding robberies committed in Yorkshire and neighboring counties.
    - Cooper, Anthony Ashley, 1621-1683, 1st Earl of Shaftesbury. Letter (copy) to [Charles Howard, 1st Earl of Carlisle, 1673 Feb 3], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Endorsed: "Copy of a letter of the E. of Shaftesbury's." He writes that he will not come to court during this Parliament "until the king thinketh frequent new parliaments as much his Interest as they are the people['s] rights..."
    - Gurdon, A. ALS to Sir Henry Capel, Lincolns Inn, 1675 Aug 12 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Unidentified
      - AL (draft) to unknown recipient, [c.1680] (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Endorsed: "Copy of a letter about the Lord Shaftesbury."
      - AL to unknown recipient, London, [1676/7] Feb 16 (Box 1, Folder 23)
        Newsletter describing the reaction of Lords Buckingham, Shaftesbury, Salisbury, and Wharton on learning that they would be punished for their attempts to dissolve the present parliament.
      - AL to Edward Proggers, 1667 Apr 10 (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Newsletter, endorsed: "a letter out of the north without a name, 1667."
- Danby Papers, Series II; 0.25; (.5 box)
  Material concerned with the Popish Plot and Danby's impeachment is filed first. Thereafter, headings follow a roughly chronological order according to the positions held by Danby (e.g. Lord Admiral, etc.).
  - PAPERS CONCERNING THE POPISH PLOT
    - Coleman, Edward, d.1678
      - Extracts from Coleman's letters to and from various correspondents, [1674-78] (Box 2, Folder 25)
        Includes Sir William Throckmorton, Father Sheldon, and Monsieur de St. Germain. Many of the letters were included in Sir Robert Southwell's report to the Privy Council. The papers also contain a copy of the declaration found in Coleman's papers.
      - Extracts from various informants' testimony, c.1678 (Box 2, Folder 26)
        6 extracts from examinations of various informers. Mentioned are William Bedloe, Lady Abergavenny, Mr. Jenison, Mr. Pratt, and Dr. Tong.
      - Abstract of the proceedings of the Council concerning "Dr. Tong's paper.", 7 Sep. 1678
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Oversize, Box 3, folder 54
  - PAPERS RELATED TO DANBY'S IMPEACHMENT
    - Drafts and memoranda, c.1679-81 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      12 items, including notes on speeches made in the House of Commons by Sir H[ugh] W[yndham] and Sir John Trevor; private instructions sent by Danby, requesting that the recipient "wait upon all my Friends" and "bespeak their Kindness in my business"; also, a list of supporters and opponents in the House of Lords.
  - PAPERS OF THE ADMIRALTY OFFICE (1671-73)
    - Documents relating to Naval affairs, 1671-73 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      10 items, including orders for payment, signed by various officials, including Lord Brouncker, Sir Thomas Allin, John Pepys and J. Ernle, and letters of the Earl of Danby.
  - PAPERS OF THE TREASURY
    - Letter to the Commissioners of the Nottinghamshire poll, 1667 Mar 25 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Signed by Charles Fitzroy, 1st Duke of Southampton, and Anthony Ashley Cooper.
    - Copy of Commission of Accounts and proposals for the increase and collection of revenue, 1667-77 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Includes information on collecting excise and other revenue in England and Ireland, including proposals for the coal trade and requests for patents for collection of the excise. 12 items total.
      See also: Oversize, Box 3, folder 55.
    - Documents concerning revenue projections, 1673-75 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      Includes a 24p MS proposal concerning the excise revenue with notes in the autograph of Danby [c.1675]. 15 items total.
    - Documents concerning military expenditures, 1673-75 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Includes memoranda of Sir Stephen Fox (1627-1716), expenditures of the garrison at Tangiers, and sailors' wages for 1673. 11 items total.
    - Documents concerning expenses of the royal household, 1673-74 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      Drafts of expenditures, proposals for improvements, financial situation of the royal household at Michaelmas 1673, estimate of expenses for the Great Wardrobe for 1674. 13 items total.
    - Miscellaneous papers related to state finance and expenditure, 1673-1708 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      Includes copies of the civil list for 1696 and 1708. 5 items.
      See also: Oversize, Box 3, folder 56.
  - DOCUMENTS CONCERNING THE WEST RIDING MILITIA
    - Two militia muster rolls, [c.1670s] (Box 2, Folder 35)
      Two MSS bound, 11p and 8p, which contain muster rolls. The 11p MS contains names of soldiers under respective officers while the 8p MS is a list of 'common soldiers' by village or area (e.g. Wentworth, Brightside, Sheffield, etc.).
    - Documents pertaining to commissions and musters, 1661-72 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Includes a warrant signed by George Villiers, 2nd Duke of Buckingham, (1627-1687), 1661, and letters and memoranda concerning the state of the militia addressed to Danby. 13 items total.
    - Correspondence, memoranda, and drafts, 1677-78 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      Includes lists of deputy lieutenants, for 1677, correspondence to Danby from the deputy lieutenants concerning plans for muster, troop strength, etc. In- includes correspondence from Sir Godfrey Copley (d. 1709); Sir Henry Goddricke (1642-1704); Sir Ralph Knight; William Hayes; and Richard Blanshard. 31 items total.
      See also: Oversize, Box 3, folder 57.
    - Drafts and copies of letters of com- mission for Deputy Lieutenants, c. 1678 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      Vellum and paper, some including Danby's seal as Lord Treasurer. X items total.
      See also: Oversize, Box 3, folder 58.
  - MISCELLANEOUS DOCUMENTS OF AFFAIRS OF STATE (1660-1700)
    - List of queries put to the Duke of Buckingham in the House of Commons, 1674 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      Contemporary copy of the queries concerning the Commons' attack on Buckingham as the author of the French alliance and as a promoter of arbitrary government. Endorsed by the Earl of Danby.
    - Draft of a speech of Charles II, 1679 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      Draft of a speech delivered by Charles II before parliament. Endorsed: "Draught of the K.'s Speech in Mr. Charles Bertie's Hand."
    - Copy of the bill to exclude the Duke of York, 1681
      See: Oversize, Box 3, folder 59. 6p, bound at the top. Copy of the proposal to exclude the Duke of York from the royal succession.
    - Copy of the proceedings against Edmund Fitzharris at the court of the King's Bench, 1681 May 7-May 11 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      12p, copy, addressed to the Earl of Danby.
    - Miscellaneous state papers, c.1660-1700 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      Includes a copy of King Charles II's proclamation of peace with the States General of the Netherlands, 1667; list of payments made by the French ambassador to William Chiffinch (for Charles II), 1670-72; copy of a dispensation to Obadiah Walker, 1686; abstract of Royal Patents to Sir Robert Long; copy of orders by the king in council, 1667 Jan 31; a copy of a prophecy made by John Sadler, 1661; and a document concerning the case of Col. Thomas King and his actions to secure the Tower of London in 1688. 23 items total.
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - The principle reasons for the great fail of rents occasioned by the low price of corn, c.1675 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      Anonymous MS concerned with the efforts of brewers in London to fix barley prices and the subsequent impact upon land rents.
    - Narrative of the growth of Whigg, [c.1690s] (Box 2, Folder 44)
      An anonymous MS "shewing the defects in these measures which have been taken to suppress them from time to time with a modest advice touching a remedy." 10p.
    - Question upon the prorogation of parliament, [early 18th c.] (Box 2, Folder 45)
      Anonymous MS of legal inquiry concerning "whether a prorogation of Parliament extended beyond twelve months to be not by construction of law a dissolution." 3p.
- Later Osborne and Godolphin Papers, 1686-1709; Series III; 0.25; (.5 box)
  - Glarwood, George. ALS to Edward Osborne, Viscount Latimer, 1686/7 Jan 14 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Godolphin, Sir William, 1634?-1696. 4 documents concerning members of the Godolphin family, 1696-97 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Includes a copy of the wills of Sir Sir William Godolphin and his sister, Penelope Godolphin, and a Latin epitaph on Henry Godolphin (1648-1733).
  - Howard, R. ALS to Edward Osborne, Viscount Latimer, Long Acre, London, 1684 Apr 27 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Campbell, Hugh, d. 1731, Earl of Loudon. 2 ALS to [Sidney Godolphin, 1st Earl of Godolphin], Edinburgh, [1706] Aug 26, Sep 2 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Concerning the proposed Treaty of Union with Scotland.
  - Finch, Daniel, 1647-1730, 2nd Earl of Nottingham. ALS to Sidney Godolphin, 1st Earl of Godolphin, Whitehall, 1702 Sep 2 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    Concerning Marlborough's campaign.
  - Pelham, Henry, 1695?-1754. ALS to [?Thomas Osborne, 4th Duke of Leeds], 1748 Aug 11 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Talbot, Charles, 1666-1718, 1st Duke of Shrewsbury. 2 ALS to [Sidney Godolphin, 1st Earl of Godolphin], Rome, 1704 Jul 5, Sep 8, n.s. (Box 2, Folder 52)
    Current general news.
  - Wharton, Thomas, 1648-1715, 1st Marquis of Wharton. ALS to [Sidney Godolphin, 1st Earl of Godolphin], 1709 Aug 15 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    Concerns passage of a money bill.
- Oversize, 1670-1700; 1.75; (1 box)
  Oversize contains material from Series II, arranged in series order.
  - PAPERS CONCERNING THE POPISH PLOT
    - Abstract of the proceedings in Council concerning "Dr. Tong's paper.", 7 Sep. 1678 (Box 3, Folder 54)
      Summary of the testimony given to the special council apppointed by Charles II. Concerns the allegations of a "Jesuit conspiracy" made by Dr. Tong in a letter sent to Danby on 3 September. 1p.
  - PAPERS OF THE TREASURY
    - Copy of Commission of Accounts, 1667 (Box 3, Folder 55)
      Also contains list of profits of the Alienacion Office for 1676.
    - Miscellaneous papers related to state finance and expenditure, 1708 (Box 3, Folder 56)
      Account sheet for the financing and cost of rebuilding St. Paul's, 1708
  - DOCUMENTS CONCERNING THE WEST RIDING MILITIA
    - Correspondence, memoranda, and drafts, 1677-78 (Box 3, Folder 57)
      List of deputy lieutenants' regiments and officers.
    - Drafts and copies of letters of com- mission for deputy lieutenants, c.1678 (Box 3, Folder 58)
      Vellum and paper, some including Danby's seal as Lord Treasurer.
  - MISCELLANEOUS DOCUMENTS OF AFFAIRS OF STATE
    - Copy of the bill to exclude the Duke of York, 1681 (Box 3, Folder 59)
      6p, bound at top. Copy of the proposal to exclude James Stuart, the Duke of York, from the royal suc- cession.